[Music]
hey Mark how's it going fine yourself
great man great great great great to
have you back good to be back although
the word round two makes it sound like a
boxing match yeah no it's just uh it's
just a way to keep track of the
conversations nothing
serious how you doing are you still in
Boston mark
no I I got back um two days ago okay how
was the how was the tri it was actually
a slightly nightmarish flight to Boston
I got um diverted eventually to New York
okay and um and then it was of a
shambles but apart from that part of it
I mean I ended up losing almost a whole
day but the once I did get there
scientifically it was just fantastic I
really enjoyed it I know I saw some of
you did a presentation at tough um yeah
it seemed like a really great time I did
a presentation which I was happy with I
was very happy with how it was received
by some people who I respect you know so
it's it's it's it's good um to to get
good feedback from Minds that you admire
and then there was also the added
dimension of Mike's lab I mean I know
about his work but to actually visit his
lab it's just quite
extraordinary I'm actually to touch on
that at some point because I wrote a
note here about the collaborations you
guys are doing friston Fields Le I mean
there's so much happening here and it's
it's so exciting from the outside I
asked Mike about this about a week ago
and it just seems incredible he left me
with a nice question for you right at
the very end what is the meaning of life
you know I tweeted this to you Mike also
he just wants to know he thinks you
actually might provide a very valuable
answer to this cuz he thinks that your
background in neuropsychology will help
enhance this answer so give us
that well um actually I'd forgotten that
you tweeted that I wish i' I wish I'd
prepared an answer because that's not
the kind of question one likes to
receive what is the meaning of life
especially when you're expecting a
serious and and and uh and satisfying
answer so
um what what I would say first of all is
we must distinguish between uh the the
the sort of uh purpose of life and the
meaning of life the purpose of life is
very easy to discern it's to keep on
going being alive you know it's to to
survive and to reproduce I'm afraid is
the purpose of life described
biologically because of course life is a
biological thing and so when you speak
of what is it for it's just for keeping
it s going that's all it's for um but
that doesn't mean that's the meaning of
life you know so I I would draw a
distinction between us as biological
organisms uh which are just struggling
to um resist the second law of
Thermodynamics and and and keep going or
resisted for as long as we can and then
we lose you know the I would like to
distinguish between that and the the the
being of an organism you know our
subjective existence that's where I
think the word meaning uh is appropriate
it's like okay so I'm here what what am
I going to you know what should what
should I do with this other than just
you know Carry On from a biological
point of view existing as a as a living
thing what is the meaning of all of this
um and my
um my emphasis of course is on feelings
um
as you know I think subjectivity is
fundamentally um constituted by feeling
we are feeling beings that's what being
is to be to to for the you know that
phrase there's an organism that that
there's something it is like to be that
organism it it is a feeling organism um
now our feelings uh again as you know
because I've spoken to you about before
they are just the way in which we become
aware of our needs so so you could look
at that biologically you could say well
the reason why for example the reason
why pleasure is attached to sexuality is
because that's how our species
reproduces and so from a purely
biological point of view sex is
pleasurable uh because that's that's got
to do with that purpose side of things
the meaning side of it I mean why do we
actually have sex as subject objects you
know as as feeling beings it's it's not
because we're trying to do our
biological Duty you know not at all um
we we we in fact most of the time that
we have sex we are hoping not to
reproduce so it's there really is it's
not a small distinction it's it's it's a
very different thing um what we're doing
in terms of in terms of what motivates
us as sentient beings as subjects um has
has to do with so it's for that reason
for me it has been a very important part
of the meaning of my life is to try and
understand you know what is this what is
feeling uh what what what is it what is
it all about um and to try and
understand it I think that that's been a
very worthwhile quest uh to try to
understand what is it to be and what is
feeling and um the the I person can't
find a more um a more um worthwhile way
of spending my brief period of
biological existence trying to
understand what what it is what it is
all about um and
uh I'm I'm perfectly happy with the
meaning of my life from from that point
of view now I used sex as a as an
example because it's so easy to see the
biological versus the subjective but it
applies to all of our needs you know
what we what we're living is it's like
let me take something even more praic
you know we don't uh we we eat chocolate
and sweets and stuff you know because
they taste nice the the reason they
taste nice is because they've got high
energy content that's what makes them
taste nice but we're not thinking oh you
know the what I really need to do is get
high energy supplies what we're doing is
saying I really like this you know so um
the the other main thing I've done in my
life is is is train in and practice
psychoanalysis and that's really uh you
could easily say uh that it's not the
only way of going about it but it is one
of the it's a it's like like the many
Eastern traditions where like meditative
traditions and so on in fact I met a
very senior Buddhist when was in Boston
now and so I spoke quite a bit um or
interacted quite a bit with with um with
that way of approaching the same task
which is you know really trying to
properly confront what is it to be what
is it to be mortal what is what are
these feelings really for what do I feel
about them what are what what are my
values what do I want to do in relation
to my felt needs which include needs to
uh not only survive and reproduce and
eat uh but but you know to have fun uh
Play It's terribly important you know to
recognize that has been a a real
Discovery in my life and and to
recognize it as a you know as an
experien of of the need to play the need
to have fun to rec so the more I've
understood about you know how minds work
and how my mind works the the better I'm
able to enjoy my mind uh and and
recognize that it's inevitable that
there's no such thing as a conflict free
existence you know all of our different
needs are they they need to be balanced
with each other uh and you kind of you
become more sanguin about it all and and
allow yourself to appreciate you know
what what it is what it is to to and
foregrounding feelings has been a a very
important um not not only because of my
own work in relation to the to the
neuroscience of feeling but also you
know in relation to psychoanalysis
getting to know your own feelings face
up to them face up to your conflicts
Ponder how are you going to deal with
them recognize you're never going to be
Exempted from conflicts and so on so I
suppose um what is that um there's a
phrase the examined life yesam life is
not worth living yeah and uh and also
the old you know know thyself I think
that's
the that's that's that is the that is
the meaning that you end up that I end
up realizing that's the best you can do
with with life is to is to is to wonder
at it to ponder it to try to understand
it to reflect upon it to be fully alive
in the sense of being alive you know not
not not biological life but but
experiential life um to to to to to to
to ponder it to reflect on it to study
it to to wonder at it to appreciate it I
think I think we're similar in that case
and this podcast obviously embodies that
that Curiosity that that sort of this
quest for us to try and Conquer his mind
when I spoke to Mike this that question
came at the very end and I remember it's
because apparently Mike gets a lot of
emails lately regarding the meaning of
life and and he's not a psychologist so
he doesn't have this background he's not
a philosopher so for him he gets gets
caught in a between a rock and a hot
place because he's obviously not an
expert in those fields so he said he'd
rather just shift that onto
you I'm not surprised he gets uh emails
like that because his work I mean it it
really is um pretty fundamental in terms
of you know what what are what is an
organism and and and and you know what
is what is life right at the most basic
level of single cells and so on it's
it's fantastically interesting what he's
doing it's pretty cool and I know that
you guys you were in Boston you went you
visited Mike's lab um first I don't know
if for all of those curious do you want
to tell us about that
experience it was an extraordinary
experience I know about his
work um but knowing about something and
experiencing it is you know are two
different things and that's like of your
work pretty much you actually got to
feel it yeah so
um the the the the main species that
he's studying uh he studies various
different organisms but these little
worms um that are the the first thing
that's astonishing about them uh and to
actually encounter one such worm um is
is that they're Immortal I mean
literally Immortal you know they they've
been around for millions and millions of
years they don't die they just subdivide
um and so there's no mixing of genomes
you know it's the same genome carrying
on and on and on and on and um so in
some very real sense you know you're
looking at a many millions of years old
creature and what's more it's looking
back at you it's got these big
eyes so there's this encounter with with
with with an immortal being um they they
um then the the fact that they
subdivide um you know is what in what
led Mike to to study the mechanisms of
morphogenesis how does an organism know
what it's meant to become you know um
and there how at the most fundamental
mechanistic level does that happen then
you can chop these creatures in half and
the the head grows a tail and the tail
grows a head um and so you know having
studied what those mechanisms are um he
started to fiddle about with them
because if you really do understand the
mechanism in fact the one way in which
you can convince yourself and your
colleagues that you do understand the
mechanism is to is to make an
intervention in it and predict what the
consequences will be and if you can
predictably control that mechanism then
you really do understand it and so as
you no doubt know he made a two-headed
worm you know by manipulating the the
the these bioelectrical fields that are
what guide the mor for Genesis so I also
met a two-headed worm which was which
was something to behold you know I mean
it's just really
extraordinary and um and then when those
worms subdivide they subdivide into
two-headed worms so he sort of created a
new species yeah I think I think those
are the ones he calls xenobots eh I'm
not sure if that is the xenobots are
yeah say he they various you know like
he takes a tadpole and and shifts where
its eyes going to be and they end up
with this frog that seiz out of its
house and but I mean all these things
could be um they they they could be
perceived as as ghoulish or or or even
as in you know in all sorts of ways
inappropriate so it's important to
remember that ultimately what it's all
about uh is you know to what extent can
we translate this basic knowled from the
lab to the clinic and it has it has
profound potential implications for how
we treat amputees um how we deal with um
you know situations where currently one
has to do organ transplants uh the
possibility of being able to regenerate
a diseased organ rather than to
transplant it and so on I mean the the
possibilities are are amazing but then
in terms of you said um you know what
are we doing in terms of
collaborations the the the main overlap
it's it's the main overlap because
actually there are many ways in which
our our um interests and and research uh
intersect but the main overlap is um I
believe and there's a long story that
attaches to that so I'll just come to
the conclusion you know I believe for
for lots of very good scientific reasons
um that the fundamental form of
Consciousness is feeling and feelings
enable us to know how well or badly
we're doing in terms of remaining within
our our our viable bounds so moving out
of homeostasis feels bad moving back
towards homeostasis feels good and um
the the what this does that's that's um
that's an an adaptation Beyond mere
homeostasis because many homeostatic
mechanisms are purely autonomic you
there's no feeling involved like blood
pressure regulation and so on um by
being able to feel homeostasis feel how
well or badly you're doing in terms of
your attempts to to to maintain your
biological balance enables you to change
your mind uh this is not working so
before it's too late you you you you you
alter um your your your behavior you
change your policy and um so this why
that's so important is it enables a
creature to survive in an uncertain
unpredicted environment um so you can
come up with novel solutions to Life's
Problems by feeling your way through the
problem you're not you're not limited to
to a single stereotyped response when
you find yourself in a situation for
which you do not have an innate uh uh uh
a um phenetically given response you can
feel your way through the situation and
come up with a novel response that is
what I've just described is the very
basis of voluntary Behavior you know
which is no small thing and then we
learn from from the from the experience
and so we can we can adapt to uh
unpredicted situations and God knows
there many of those in life we can we
can do them during our own onto genetic
development now the crucial thing is
that with Mike fiddling about with these
uh
creatures I mean what the problem of
what do you do when you've got two heads
is a novel problem it's it's not
something that that species was prepared
for by Evolution what happens if you
move the eye um to an unexpected
location you know this this is not
something for which there is any
possibility of there being an an an
automatic in inborn um solution and so
uh I'm very interested in in what way is
the the the sorts of things that these
um uh uh very much simpler creatures
than ourselves the way that they solving
these novel problems uh raises questions
of you know how far down does feeling Go
is is is a creature like this worm
feeling its way through a problem
because if it is you know then wow I
mean I thought um that I had uh set a
cut cut among the pigeons when I told my
colleagues I don't believe that cortex
is the the the the organ of
Consciousness I think that you know the
the reticulate activating system and per
aqueductal gray you know these
structures that we share with all
vertebrates so for example with fishes
you know
um I thought this was Radical but if it
goes down even even more than that you
know then the implications are just you
know
gigantic um so that's that's where my
work overlaps with with Mike's um and
that's what the the the collaborations
and there's also Chris Fields I don't
know if you know
him and and Richard Watson you know so
we we've all been in fact Mike is a
great
um he he he he us he gets the right
people together yes um it seems like
collaboration yeah he I asked him for a
name you could just give me like a a
nice name of this group he said he
called it the field of diverse
intelligence are you happy with
that I can't remember what he he he gave
the his lab was called something like
the center for possible selves or
something like that yeah know this is
very C in that regard but I was I was I
was just it's so fascinating to see all
these great minds come together CU then
I told him it's almost like the Avengers
of mind getting together trying to solve
the hard problem it's pretty cool so
from our perspective we just want to say
thanks tell me so sorry continue I I
think that we are living through a sort
of a golden age um if not of
Neuroscience uh um as a whole certainly
Consciousness studies um I I think we
really are at at a at a very interesting
and important time in the in the history
of of that field yeah it it seems to be
just escalating so much more and and so
much faster that hopefully we're around
to see what happens next me it's kind of
it's kind of disappointing knowing that
we're we're at this Forefront and you
never know if you're just going to be
alive long enough to see it do you ever
get that sort of anticipation
anxiety well um it's not the way I
experienced that very issue that you're
discussing uh it it's more from the
other end the way I experience it it is
that um when you go against the grain um
you know when you say something like I
just said now you know I believe that a
child who's got no cortex uh that this
is this is a conscious being that that
there's something it's like to be such a
child it it's it it really doesn't win
you um
a universal approval you know people
start
saying you know well if if you go
against the compact majority view in a
science this your science your science
defends itself yes um and so what I'm
leading up to saying is that um I have
found more courage than I might
otherwise have um have had um I'm
willing to take risks and to say well
you know I know that this is going to um
put many noses out of joint I know many
people are going to think I'm a Nutter
you know that I've lost my way or
whatever and I'm I'm I'm less anxious
about that than I otherwise would have
been because I know you know you only
live once and uh as you can see I'm not
a kid you know so I I'm just going to
throw everything I have at it and try
and try and make as much progress as I
can uh regardless of the um not
regardless of all consequences because I
am very concerned about the ethical
consequences of some of the issues we're
dealing with uh so it's not it's not I
don't care about any of the consequences
it's that I don't care about the
consequences for my reputation um that's
what I mean yeah so you've lost that
that that that worry about the trivial
stuff you're more focused on the bigger
picture yeah well I it's because I
realize it is the bigger picture you
know the there there's there's times uh
in my life earlier in my life when I
have been very thrown by the fact that
um I mean just to take a
very earlier in my career um when I made
some discoveries that made me realize
that what my entire field believed about
the brain mechanism of dreaming was
wrong you know that that that dreams are
not generated by um the part of the
brain that generates REM sleep that REM
sleep and dreams are not the same thing
you know um it it was really a hell of a
a hell of a thing to have all of your
seniors you know all of the the great
authorities in the field uh all just
just uh be being um um you know very
hostile because uh you were you know you
you're spoiling the party you know we
you're going against the status quo
nobody likes that nobody likes that that
complete but I have a note on that so
the exact point you're talking about it
I've written down some notes so I think
we'll touch on that soon let's start at
the beginning Mark so the the the whole
focus of this conversation for everyone
watching or listening is on dreams and
the hard problem of Consciousness it's a
paper I'll put a link in uh in the
description and uh very great paper as
always um read many of your papers in
the past you even know that I used used
one of your papers in Frist for my own
dissertation back when I was writing it
so um always a pleasure to read your
work Mark and yeah I'm looking forward
to this first do you want to start with
how dreams can assist us with this
approach to the hard problem of
Consciousness um well look I I have a
great many things to say about dreams in
general but I'm I'm taking uh your
question uh in the narrow way that I
that I think I heard it you're saying I
think before you do that because I see
my next question is probably will
address what you want to tell me we
spent 20% of all of our sleep dreaming
tell me
why well that's the interesting thing
it's an embarrassment to science Nobody
Knows Why um the REM sleep was
discovered in the early
1950s um and its high correlation with
dreams uh which is a sort of 90%
correlation you know um was discovered
in the mid1 1950s too and um from then
onwards they were taken to be one and
the same thing dreaming was uh construed
as the subjective experience of REM
sleep REM sleep was construed as the
objective physiological manifestation of
of the of the of the of of the dream so
um everything that we learned in the
subsequent decades um about what REM
sleep is for because of course um it's a
hell of a lot easier to study the
mechanisms of something objective than
of something subjective so once that
correlation had been established the
dreams were thrown out as uh like
Slippery Fish the they were discarded uh
and we and we clung to this much more
tractable problem of what is REM sleep
what does it do uh and that that's those
are easy problems you know because you
can manipulate it causally it's very
easy and um we we
were therefore for decades um we were
studying the biological function of REM
sleep on the assumption that in so doing
we were studying the biological function
of dreams but they are doubly
dissociable phenomena you can have
dreams without REM sleep not only
outside of REM sleep but you can have
dreams if you are incapable of
generating REM sleep due to brain lesion
and conversely you can have R sleep
without any dreams if you have a lesion
to the part of the brain that generates
dreams REM is preserved damage to the
part of the brain that generates REM
dreams are preserved so they are just
simply not the same thing therefore
everything that we leared about the
biological function of REM sleep
thinking that we were learning about the
biological function of Dreams is um not
wasted work because we learned a lot
about the biological function of REM
sleep but it's wasted from the point of
view of what did it teach us about
dreams it taught us next to nothing
about the function of Dreams um so uh
I'll tell you what now only in recent
years um have uh have I turned my
attention to that question and used
appropriate methods because I'm not
conflating those two things with each
other um I did a pilot
study um just before Co um
and
uh and then I was of course um unable to
conclude the study uh because of Co so
I've only now couple of years later
started the bigger study so I can only
tell you uh what we found so far in our
pilot study um in order for me to tell
you that I need to just take a step
backwards and tell you that there are
two parts of the brain uh which are
essential for dreaming I mean of course
the whole brain in a way is essential
but there two parts that are really The
crucial mechanisms the one which is not
surprising is our our perceptual cortex
uh the posterior cortex especially
visual cortex it's not surprising
because what are dreams if not
perceptual phenomena and especially
visual perceptual phenomena if those if
that cortical region is damaged you
can't dream because you can't generate
the imagery that's NE you know the
actual the actual hallucination can't be
generated um but the other part is much
more interesting uh it's called the
misoc cortical mesolimbic dopamine
circuit uh and U this is a powerful
positive motivational Circuit of the
mammal brain uh uh if you stimulate that
circuit electrically or chemically it
produces the most uh animated
exploratory
um reward seeking behaviors um in in in
the animal now that circuit is essential
for dreams uh uh if that's damaged you
also can't dream and so you know that
raises all sorts of interesting
questions um but the the the the one
that I was interested in was how on
Earth in the middle of
sleep with this um as I said it
generates the most powerful exploratory
Behavior is it it when you look at the
the dreaming brain and you see that
switched on you know like a Christmas
tree you think how on Earth does this
thing just lie there sleeping you know
it's it seems like a absolute Paradox so
the the hypothesis was that the
hallucinated dream it's a kind of
virtual exploratory and other kinds of
emotional motivated Behavior Uh that
that that that happens instead of real
Behavior so the way way that the animal
um um executes its motive and when I say
animal of course I'm including ourselves
that that
um where this motivational urge or surge
goes to is into this imagined activity
this hallucinated virtual um behavior of
the dream which means that if you can't
dream due to damage to the posterior
cortex if you can't generate the imagery
then you should you should wake up
because because the dream is there to to
enable you to continue sleeping that was
the
hypothesis and it's a lovely hypothesis
because it's entirely counterintuitive
most people would think if you can't
dream you'll sleep better but on this
hypothesis if you can't dream uh you
will your sleep will be your sleep will
be disturbed and so in our pilot study
what we found was that on steroids uh
you know you have never seen such
terrible sleep as you get in these
patients um who can't dream due to due
to posterior cortical damage um they
have sleep onset insomnia sleep
maintenance insomnia they have they have
know massively more
Awakenings and and and sort of micro
Awakenings what we call arousals and
microarousals um the Sleep efficiency
index is off the charts different Total
Sleep time off the charts different so
the one thing that um that that although
it's only a pilot study so far but the
results were so clear-cut I I'm prepared
to say it publicly you know the one
thing that I believe we can say
empirically um we we we have we have
demonstrated is that whatever else
dreams do they enable us to stay asleep
uh uh in the in the uh face of of
arousals of things that would otherwise
that would otherwise arouse us let's not
forget REM sleep is itself an arousal
State you know it's it's it's uh when it
was first discovered it was called
paradoxical sleep that was how come
you're able to stay asleep when your
brain is so aroused so I'm saying that
whatever else dreams do they are
guardians of sleep uh they they enable
us to to to not have to wake up uh when
we are motivated to to to act uh to to
to do something on the basis of um of
arousals just are homeostatic deviation
so on the basis of homeostatic
deviations and Mark in terms of um
energy consumption is this is this worth
it is this constant need to to
experience worth the tradeoff
well remember it's in a sense it's the
opposite uh of the the question is you
know um can we afford not to sleep
that's true so you know you the for the
whole restitutive function of sleep uh
you can't do without that it does
there's a hell of a lot of repair work
and and um and um housekeeping that is
done by the body and the Brain uh and
including in when I say housekeeping
including memory consolidation processes
you know how you process what you've
leared during the during the day um
there's a lot of very important work
that is done um by the body and the
Brain while you're asleep and if you if
if you don't give yourself enough of
that you're a doctor you know how bad it
is to not sleep you know it's it's it's
a very serious thing to to be deprived
of sleep for your health so it's it's
can we afford not to sleep and and the
energies the energy uh um the work that
needs to be done in order to maintain
sleep is is well worth the expenditure
see it's it's almost intuitive when you
think about it I mean we the idea of
this I mean because you when you think
about the average human we don't really
want to not experience it's almost like
there's this constant need to continue
to have a continuous spectrum of
experience that's why a lot of people
fear going under anesthesia I mean it's
um they know there's almost a switching
off of of this this shutdown of the
whole Human Experience do you feel like
that make
sense uh with yeah I I think that um or
is it different somehow no no it's I
think that what you're saying is is is
is true but there are also things um
which contradict it and um I will I will
give you um I think there three things I
need to say about that the one is the
opposite of what you said which is that
we want to we want to retain
homeostasis um so so moving out of
homeostasis generates negative feelings
you know it's like um air hunger or or
sleepiness or pain or whatever these are
all deviations from
homeostasis um and pleasurable feelings
are uh returns towards homeostasis but
when you're in homeostasis you feel
nothing it's satiation so you know I'm
hungry that's bad I eat that's good
until I've had enough uh and then you
know it's it's it's over same with sleep
same with thirst same with everything so
that's the first thing I wanted to say
is that in terms of homeostasis for the
most part actually what we're trying to
do uh is get out of the zone of feeling
and into the zone of automaticity into
the zone of satiation um actually feel
satiated well you feel satiation
satiation as you come to the end of the
of the return to homeostasis but then
that particular homeostat is off the
radar it's you you're not busy thinking
I'm I'm not hungry I'm not thirsty I'm
I'm not sexually aroused I'm you know
I'm not sleepy it's just not there it's
not it's not it's not it's not on the
agenda you're feeling uh those things
which are going well or
badly but once you are uh uh uh at the
destination of
those regulatory mechanisms then they no
longer are are are registered in
Consciousness so that as I said that
first thing I've said of three things
I'm going to say that that's the
opposite of what you were saying however
um here's the second thing one of those
stats is the very one I was talking
about when I said this misoc cortical
misol liic dopamine system that has to
do with the seing drive the exploratory
foraging uh Drive what what some people
call the epistemophilic drive um and and
how that homeostat works is is is quite
different from the others um it's its
set point is is is I am engaging with
novelty I'm engaging with what I don't
know I'm engaging with what is uncertain
um and if that sounds um paradoxical
it's not it's because uncertainty is
dangerous uh you know so so if if you
have the opportunity to engage
proactively with uncertainty now then
you'll have less uncertainty later so
what you're doing is actually building a
better predictive model of the world
you're you're engaging with the world
and and better
understanding how it works which in the
long run uh enables you to better
survive um in that world so the the the
the thing that you just spoke of when
you said don't we always want to keep on
that's fundamentally driven by this it's
not only seeking but it's fundamentally
driven by the seeking uh the the the
seeking homeostat um and then the third
thing I wanted to say is that from all
of this um voluntary behavior of us
engaging with the with the world uh uh
trying to uh find how do I get into back
to where I need to be uh we learn from
that experience the conscious experience
is the feeling your way through the
problem then you lay down new
predictions based on what what you
learned from that experience and there
um the the the biological ideal is to
have predictions which are so reliable
that you don't have to feel your way
through the problem again so that's
again a trend towards zombom that in
fact what we want is to have predictions
that are so reliable uh that we that we
don't um they don't need
reconsolidation uh and so this is what
we call non declarative memory you know
these these these things that we just
know how to do like how to drive a car
you don't think what you know how does
this work you just know how to do it how
to ride a bike like how to walk you know
um how to play the piano you know
whatever these these these skills that
we acquire uh they become automatized
and that is actually a good thing so
again in those situations I mean like I
don't know if you play any musical
instrument or like if you play tennis
thinking about your stroke is a very bad
thing to do you know it must just flow
and so um in that sense too although we
don't feel it that way way actually uh
unconscious automatic processes are
better than conscious deliberative ones
when it comes to and learning from
experience about how to meet how to meet
your needs okay now it's um so let's say
so you had this hypothesis you've done
the studies um you've already uncovered
quite a lot U there's obviously a lot
more to come but to you've already
touched briefly on this but I think
let's go into a bit more because there's
the goal old standard I've wrote on in
neuropsychology where you guys discover
okay REM sleep versus Dream Within the
brain stem when there's brain stem
lesions and cortical lesions there's
clear differences in REM sleep and dream
sleep do you want to run through those
and exactly what those lesions
are yeah I I actually already have um
said this so so let me just be a little
bit more precise um the the the
mesocortical molic dopamine system
starts in the ventral tegmental area uh
which is sort of at the transition
between midbrain and dianlin uh IT
projects upwards to the nucleus
accumbent which is in the the ventral
strium the underneath part of the basil
ganglia that's the sort of main
destination but it also projects uh
beyond that uh up to frontal cortex and
also down to amydala so it's this it's
the a very big part of the medial for
brand bundle uh damage damage um
anywhere in that circuit from the vental
segmental area upwards um certainly up
to and including the nucleus cumbent uh
but we've also had patients where it's
anterior to the nuclear cir cumbent they
they stop dreaming um the other area as
I said earlier it's posterior
cortex um it it is uh in particular um
that there two sites where we see
cessation of dreaming and I say two
sites it's really a continuous site but
it goes
from the the the the inferior parietal
lobule down to the convexity of the
temporal lobe but then
also around into the medial surface
along the occi temporal uh the medial
surface so it's basically um it's
basically a posterior Association cortex
predominantly visual but not exclusive
but by no means exclusively visual so
lesions there those patients stop
dreaming but they tend to recover they
tend to recover
um in one study that I did I I followed
up 44 patients for a year uh and only
two of them were still not dreaming but
the vast majority recover within six
months in fact and one of the reasons
it's difficult to do research uh of the
kind I was describing to you earlier
when I said we were taking patients with
the posterior lesions who could not
dream for that reason and but the the
the that dopamine system was was working
fine um we wanted to see whether they
will whether their sleep will be
disturbed which as I say it was but many
of our research participants recovered
in the middle of while we were studying
them because dreaming Tes tend it's a
very robust phenomenon dreaming I think
for the very reason that I said to you
earlier that it's it's um if it has a
sleep protective function then it's a
very important thing you when you first
started out in the field you you've done
a lot you've already done so much
pioneering work in in dreaming um what's
broughten you what's brought you back to
this is it the link to Consciousness
which we're obviously going to touch on
us soon but was it that
link yes um in fact uh when I studied
dreams uh which was I started my
research in that area in the
1980s and uh I must tell you you know
people don't realize uh those days uh
Consciousness uh was not a respectable
topic you know I mean can you believe it
even in neuros Psychology you know which
you would think you know psychology
hello doesn't that have something to do
with Consciousness it was no the only
respectable topic uh as far as
Consciousness was concerned was not the
subjective EXP experience of anything it
was it was the brain mechanisms of the
of of of of sleep and wakefulness you
know so the the how how uh the Sleep
waking cycle uh is regulated and uh that
the discovery of REM sleep was within
that tradition you know the the these
arousal states that occur during the
sleeping part of the Sleep waking cycle
and so I stud
dreams uh I actually was studying brain
mechanisms of sleep and dreaming and
sleep was the intrusion of wakeful I
mean dreams or the intrusion of
wakefulness into sleep so wakefulness
was a respectable topic and so you know
I dressed up what I was doing as
studying sleep and wakefulness dreams
being wakefulness in in so um the the um
the discovery of the brain mechanisms of
dreaming at that time took me
necessarily down into the basic arousal
mechanisms of the brain stem but bearing
in mind that it particularly took me to
this one arousal mechanism which is the
dopaminergic one this is um this is not
just switching on and off the lights
it's an emotional motivational mechanism
and so that made me aware um how um made
me interested in the fact that the brain
these brain staral mechanisms are the
brain mechanisms of emotion and and and
that led me to to working with Yak PP
because Yak PP was the was the only
person who who said you know these these
brain stem arousal mechanisms generate
affect they they generate emotion they
generate feeling and um then that so
that was the second stage of my work you
know from from from sleep and dreaming
to emotion uh and then the realization
which is the the the phase of my work
that I'm in now that these mechanisms
that generate feeling and affect and
emotion are the very same mechanisms
that generate Consciousness itself so
that the foundational Elemental form of
Consciousness is affective feeling and
uh so it's you know it sounds as if I've
been all over the park but actually it's
really quite a straight line um it is I
mean and and obviously in your paper you
you lay this out perfectly you talk
about okay this of course if this is
effective feeling and if we're
experiencing constantly within this
dream state it must be something that's
necessary during Consciousness well in
conscious experience so this is a
perfect place to actually look because
you don't have to Consciousness can
occur outside dreams have to include
some sort of a conscious experience in a
sense because it exactly yeah now that's
a very interesting point what you just
said there um so you know one of the
reasons that I um
uh focused rather on the brain stem than
the
cortex which also didn't win me any
friends you know it's it's really to to
to say in in neuros pychology that the
cortex is not the organ of Consciousness
is is really to say something that goes
very very very much Against the Grain
but but but a strong reason why I did
that I mean there many reasons why I did
that when I say reasons I mean you know
there's much scientific evidence that
led me to conclude that um but within
that body of evidence is the fact that
the cortex can do just about all of its
cortical things without being conscious
yes you know so I mean
things that that only the cortex can do
like recognize faces read with
comprehension and so on you can read
with comprehension and your behavior
will be altered by what you've read
without any conscious awareness of
having seen anything at all so um most
of the re when I say most I mean really
just about all of the research uh on
trying to to to identify what they call
the neural correlative Consciousness um
was was um using Vision as the cortical
Vision because that's the conscious type
of vision um as the as our model example
but as I've just said to you um the
cortex can do all of that visual
gymnastics unconsciously so you know so
so Vision even cortical vision is not an
intrinsically conscious function so why
do you think you're going to solve the
hard problem of consciousness by
studying something that is not actually
necessarily conscious uh the reticular
activating system and per aqueductal
gray these brain stem structures uh that
generate feeling um that their whole
function is to generate Consciousness
that's what that that's why it's called
the reticular activating system it
activates the cortex it's it's it's the
cortex is only I mean this is not
controversial the evidence is just like
100% there that the the cortex only is
conscious when it is aroused by the
reticular activating system magon and
marutti showed in 1949 you sever as they
did in cats the ascending fibers that
you know the axons coming up from the
reticular activating system to the
cortex the cortex loses all
Consciousness so the Consciousness is
entirely supplied by the upper brain
stem uh and it's only in recent years
that we realized that that's not just a
power our supply that Consciousness has
a content and a quality it is affect
it's feeling so we feel our way into our
otherwise unconscious cognitions so um
why that's important is
because for the hard problem is that if
you want to identify how and why does
Consciousness arise you should be
studying this basic in every sense the
foundational form of of um of
Consciousness a form that is called
feeling which has to be felt in other
words it necessarily is conscious so you
know the way David Chas put it he said
there's no cognitive function that the
explaining of its function or mechanism
will explain why it why you experience
anything and and that he's right when it
comes to vision and so on cognitive
functions but you can't say that in
relation to affect you can't say there's
no affective function you know that if
you explain its mechanism you will
explain why you experience it because
how can you explain the mechanism of
feeling without explaining why you feel
it because you know that's the whole
point of feelings is you feel them you
haven't understood the mechanism of
feeling if it doesn't explain why you
experience it you know For Heaven's Sake
so so I became interested in relation to
the hard problem I became interested in
how does the problem change uh if we
look at this proper basic fundamental
Elemental form of Consciousness called
feeling now the interesting thing and
this is why I was so interested in what
you just said um when I've said you
can't have a feeling without feeling it
it is intrinsically conscious that's the
function we should be looking at the
same applies to dreams you can't have a
dream without being conscious of it
because otherwise it's not a dream you
know the whole the the the the the the
defining feature of dreaming in is that
the unconsciousness of sleep is
punctuated by this thing called the
consciousness of a dream you know so uh
and I don't think that that's I'm I'm
not playing games here you know I'm not
I'm not playing linguistic games or
semantic games I think that there's a
deep reason why that is the case it's
because dreams are driven by affective
functions you know those those affective
functions are gener so affect is being
generated during sleep in other words
there's a problem that's Arisen for the
organism you know it's in a state of
uncertainty about something that it's
now got to deal with and the dream is a
way of dealing with that affective
arousal in other words that deviation
from where where we need to be it's it's
a it's a biological problem that has
arisen during sleep that needs a
solution and the dream is doing the work
of getting us of managing the feeling
you know it's of of of in other words of
solving the problem of of getting us
back to homeostasis it's almost like
it's so it makes so much sense that one
should study dreams in order to
understand Consciousness it's almost
like why did we neglect this for so
long oh well that's an easy question to
answer it's because you know in fact
it's the biggest problem of psychology
is psychology is the science of the mind
uh and what is mind if not something
subjective the the the defining feature
of of of mental life is that it is the
subjective being of the organism it's it
is intrinsically subjective I mean hence
um you can ever you can you can only
observe your own Consciousness you can't
observe anybody else's Consciousness
ever because they are objects you're
you're a subject you can only experience
your own subjectivity consciousness the
mind subjectivity you know these these
things are an embarrassment to science
because science aspires to objectivity
you know so how do you do science on
something you know that you can only
observe your own I know I I wrote one of
your one of your lines in the paper is
um scientists prefer objects over
subjects yes exactly and um now with
dreams it's even worse because uh you're
having a subjective experience while
you're asleep uh you know so there
there's no behavior that goes with this
uh with this mental state the person uh
the dreamer is asleep uh and so the only
way you can get access to their dream uh
is for them to wake up and remember the
dream and then report it to you so it's
a single witness uh retrospective report
of a phenomenon that we know is
notoriously forgettable uh and also
inate most of the time it's also very
hard to translate dream experience into
words you know you you you know we all
we all know that when you try to tell
your partner or something you know what
you dreamt last night you know as you're
doing it it isn't really that wasn't
really wasn't you know that doesn't
quite convey what it was like so I think
that um you know you said why didn't we
start there uh in the first place I
think that it's uh for these sorts of
reasons it's also for these sorts of
reasons that as I said to you a couple a
good few minutes ago now I said that
once the correlation between dreaming
and REM sleep had been established we
dropped the dreams and just studied the
REM sleep but please note um what grave
errors that can lead us into I mean we
lost decades uh of research um effort
because uh we we we we wanted to only
study the object Ive side um of the of
the Mind Body
correlation um the the the
um I think that let me say this the the
brain is the only thing that we know of
in the universe that has subjective
experience um and uh surely this subject
to this extraordinary quality uh it must
be doing something you know and
um if if that's the case you're never
going to understand how the brain works
unless you understand why unless you
take account of its subjectivity you
know the what the if the subjective I
mean as we all know from our own lived
lives you know you you know that what
you do is caused in large part by how
you feel you know and so if we leave
that out of the equation we're never
going to understand how that part of
nature works there's also a lot of
historical I mean you you you you've
already said this but I mean the
behaviorist movement obviously played a
big role in this also the fact that
dreams are often associated with Sigman
Freud I mean the interpretation of
Dreams is one of his biggest books and
and a lot of people misinterpret a lot
of Freud's work or because of the flaws
within it people don't take it in a
context and and then disregard a lot of
it which is incorrect I mean one of your
lines was consciousness of cortical
representations contextualize affect and
that context that context is so
important yes look let's just go back to
what you said there about the
behaviorists because there's
something that we must never forget um
you know I told you uh I don't need to
tell you the word psychology you know
means science of the mind uh and the
behaviorists excluded the psyche from
psychology you know they said no we
can't study the mental States because
they're subjective we're only going to
study behaviors I mean how absurd is
that to have psychology without the
psyche is and and the the mistake there
is to adjust the subject that you're
studying to the methods that you have
available you know you got to adjust the
methods to the thing that you're
studying um and embarrassing as
subjectivity may be to science it's
certainly exists in nature I mean the
one thing that we can all be absolutely
certain about is that we are experienc
as de told us it's the one thing you can
be sure of is that you know you exist
because you
experience and um so you know you can't
exclude it from science you got to find
methods that uh that are suited to the
study of subjectivity so that's what
Freud did uh Freud's Freud I hastened to
uh to to add for all of his mistakes
with all of his faults you know Etc
because you know
I'm not one of those people who thinks
that everything that Freud did was you
know was correct by any means but I
think that this thing that he did was
correct was to say that the the the
centerpiece of psychological science in
in other words it's you have the psych
psychological science has to has to be
adapted to how do you study subjectivity
and um so he didn't hesitate to study
subjectivity the whole his method called
free association it's basically just a
sample of the stream of Consciousness uh
uh um in a relatively controlled setting
and um and and he used the same method
to study dreams they just getting the
patient to or the research participant
to say everything that comes to
Consciousness in relation to the
remembered elements of the dream and um
in doing that he came to the not very
obvious conclusion
you know that dreams are motivated in
fact Wishful states of Mind dreams don't
look like that to to us most of them I
mean what about nightmares for example
most dreams just seem completely
incomprehensible nonsense but Freud said
no behind this you know and that's so
there you have the weakness of his
method because I mean how do you falsify
that you can't falsify it to say behind
every dream is a wish you know if it's
uh behind the dream is the wish you know
then then you can always find that wish
if if you interpreting you know like he
did that's that that's the method but
now we have new methods so you know
positron emission tomography you look at
the dreaming brain and you see that that
that motivating Wishful seeking
mechanism switching on full blast and so
you know I I I I I my uh I don't know if
you know this St but I I I became
interested in Psycho analysis uh in
large part because of my dream findings
you know it's it was um it was you know
sort
of I was trained in an era where
psychoanalysis was not part of the
University it wasn't serious science at
all you know so for me it was a really a
big surprise to discover first of all
that REM sleep is not what generates
dreams secondly that what generates
dreams is these emotional motivational
circuits and in fact the most Wishful
one that we've got you know is the one
that made me take take a second look at
Freud um I can only imagine I don't even
remember what your question was but that
was my answer to it no it's fine but I
can imagine because I remember once I
mean you've said this in other podcasts
as well but I remember you also told me
that uh studying psychoanalysis was akin
to people would describe it as almost
being an astronomer studying astrology
so ex there's so much backtracking
you're already have to do and then in
order to defend someone like Freud
probably makes it even harder at that
point um because people have so many
negative connotations to it nowadays yes
yeah that's right well think Sor sorry
no I think that um if we can if we can
re um
introduce into psychological science and
we are in our era we are you know
reintroduce the subjectivity in the full
sense of the word in other words not
this function called Consciousness but
rather you know the the actual
experiential lived life the
phenomenologic the the the qualitative
stuff that is the proper subject matter
of psychology um then you know we've we
we we've we've rein re we've got back to
where Freud started from and then we can
go Way Beyond where Freud ended yeah
know there is a field called
phenomenological Psychopathology which a
lot of people are trying to bring into
Psychiatry and psychopathology just to
assist with that lived experience aspect
of it all but but anyway Mark let's go
let's move on to the to to aect coming
as I said you that quote of yours
consciousness of cortical
representations contextualize affect um
then let's discuss those three features
of affect first and move on from there I
mean you describe them as veilance
qualia and action when to go into detail
with
that before we move on
yeah well the the thing that
distinguishes affects from other mental
States is the ve first and foremost uh
uh affects are intrinsically Veen in
other words they have an intrinsic
goodness or Badness about them um and
importantly that goodness or Badness is
goodness and Badness to me for me it's
subjective so it's it's um they are vean
subjective States objects don't have
intrinsic veence it's it's to it's it's
this it's only this subject objective
state that has this intrinsic veence
this subjective State called affect um
but pleasure and unpleasure veilance is
a continuous variable you know you you
start at this end there's unpleasure and
you carry on you know through neutral to
to pleasure it's a it's a you can
quantify it on a single scale it's it
can be reduced to to a common
denominator um but uh affects um are are
are not they are categorical variables
in the sense that it's not just I feel
good or I feel bad it's that I feel bad
about what you know so the So Hunger is
a particular need um which is different
from thirst which is another need which
is different from sleepiness which is
another need um they all of them
unpleasant uh but the they have to be
categorically distinct from each other
um because each of those needs has to be
met in that in its own right you can't
you can't say I've got eight out of 10
of um of sleepiness and four out of 10
of thirst therefore I've got 12 out of
20 of total need um or total
unpleasure um so therefore all I'm going
to do is sleep you you I'm reducing the
total number you you'll die if you don't
you don't drink also so there this is a
very important point you know I I it's
such a simple point that I think that we
can easily just sort of like skim over
it but I really want to emphasize it
that affects therefore must be
qualitatively distinct from each other
because they have to be treated as
categorical variables it's it's it's
there's no there's no alternative you
have to you have to treat treat each
need in its own right and so the
subjective experience of the veilance
has to be veilance in relation to this
one in relation to this one in relation
to this one and why that's important is
because that means that because remember
categorical variables are qualitatively
distinguished from each other eight out
of 10 of sleep is not the same thing as
eight out of 10 of of thirst you know
they are they're qualitatively different
categorical variables work like that why
that's so important is because there you
have the necessary basis for qualia
qualia have to exist in the mind in the
sense that you have these subjective
states which are intrinsically valanced
and they also are intrinsically
qualitatively distinct from each other
and I think that that's really important
in terms again of the hard problem of
Consciousness why do we have these
qualitative States well there's one very
good reason why we have them the third
aspect that you mentioned um which is
the behavior it's acting uh on those
States uh because you know they are
these are these are not nice to have you
know these are these are needs these are
phenotypic needs if you don't meet those
needs you die I mean that's how
homeostasis works so we have inbuilt
behaviors um that they reflexes or
instincts that go with each of these
different um um phenotypic needs you
know like um foraging behavior and and
sexual behavior and and and and and and
and sleep behavior and and you know Etc
um but those are we're born with those
things they're far too stereotyped
they're not they're not even nearly uh
enough to be able to enable us to meet
our needs in the great unpredictable
variety of situations that we find
ourselves in including many novel
situations and so we have to supplement
uh these uh these behaviors with um
through learning from experience uh and
and so we have in addition to these
innate predictions which we call
reflexes and instincts we have then the
full uh gamut of all of the different
things that we do and and I just want to
add this last point please note that
everything we do
ultimately if you look at it
biologically is in order to meet our
needs in order to stay alive in order to
arrive and reproduce to take us back to
that thing about the purpose of life
that we were speaking about at the
beginning of our conversation
so continue Mark sorry I was no no
that's that's that's what I wanted to
say so that's what that's what a effects
are it's it's intriguing because um I
mean at some point in your paper you
eventually bring up bring up the
knowledge argument to to sort of
solidify this aspect um I was sharing by
email with Frank Jackson about that um
try trying to get him on the show but he
says he's taking a break from social
media because I think that's one of the
best arguments to show someone an
example of I mean that that pure essence
of feeling um when Mike's episode came
out had people going at it in the
comment section you have people
discussing how because Mike at some
point had said that the only way to
truly know to truly get a conscious a
future where we can all integrate and
corporate better is if we slowly learn
what each other are experiencing more
and more and the only true way to know
what someone else is experiencing is to
actually experience what they're
experiencing because otherwise there's
no other way it's it's pretty much an
impossible reality at that point um and
then people were bringing up the
knowledge argument and saying okay well
if they have all the theory why is that
impossible do you want to touch on that
and give them an
answer the the oh
well just in case there's people uh
watching or listening who who are not
familiar with the knowledge argument uh
it it is in simplified form uh this is
my simplification of it that there's
there's there's a visual neuroscientist
named Mary
and she knows everything that there is
to know about the mechanisms of vision
you know the physical physiological
processes whereby visual information is
processed but Mary's blind that's my
simplified part of it and so she doesn't
know what it is like to see she knows
everything that's the knowledge she's
got all the knowledge about uh how
visual information is processed in the
brain but she knows nothing about what
it is like to see the actual qualitative
phenomenological experience of vision
and so Jackson's argument those days
because he's changed his mind by the way
but in 1982 when he when he published
that he said that shows that the actual
qualitative phenomenological experience
of seeing is not accounted for by the
causal physical mechanism it it it
exists in some other plane um nothing
about her knowledge of the physical
mechanisms of vision prepared Mary for
what it is like to see e even gave her
any reason to predict that there would
be something it is like to see it seems
therefore that the the the the
qualitative subjective experience of
seeing isn't necessary it doesn't do
anything it's just you know and where
does it fit into the mechanism it
doesn't that was the knowledge argument
so my response to that was that's
because as I've said previously in this
conversation because vision is not an
intrinsically conscious function you can
understand everything about how visual
information processing works because
without reference to what it is like to
see because visual information
processing can work without you having
any experiential Vision um I mean your
phone can see you the camera in your
phone sees a face recognizes the face
takes a photograph of a face remembers
their for that face all of that stuff
but there's nothing it's like to be a
camera or to be a phone and it does it
even better cu if you are if you click
take remove the nose the phone knows
exactly which parts to remove so it sees
even better than us yeah so all of this
very complicated visual information
processing can go on without any
experience now as I said earlier that
does not apply to another function so
that's the function of vision but the
function of feeling you canot explain
the function of feeling without knowing
what it is like to feel without
explaining why it feels like something
if if Mary was a affective
neuroscientist actually first of all if
Mary was an affective neuroscientist
who'd never experienced affect she would
in fact be dead because her brain stem
mechanisms that keep her alive you know
would would would not be
working and in in in a manner of
speaking that's also an important point
it's that you know this is not this is
not fluff feeling is is is has massive
causal consequences
but patients in coma you know they die
unless we keep them alive you you can't
live without without being
conscious and um you know in other words
the the Consciousness is doing something
bloody important um so so that was my
argument is that had we started with
affect rather than with vision the the
the the the knowledge problem would
never ever risen and and and and the
hard problem which which comes 30 years
later Charmers Builds on Jackson's
knowledge argument in fact he it's a
very pivotal to Charmers as whole view
that you know you can explain the
function without explaining why there's
an experience attached to the the the um
execution of that function uh that's
pretty much the essence of the hard
problem also I made a not oh sorry I
made a Nota saying unconscious feeling
is an oxymoron you also like yeah that's
a very nice one yeah but but please
remember T what I'm saying is that it's
not only that it's an oxymoron it is an
oxymoron but it's an oxymoron for a very
good reason yes you know it's and when I
say that the the that feeling is where
we should feeling is the elemental form
of Consciousness and we should study
that if we want to understand its
mechanism how it arises why it arises um
then let us not forget that the part of
the brain that generates feelings is the
part of the brain that generates
Consciousness it's like this is
intrinsically Consciousness generating
tissue so it's not just a word you know
that feeling must be felt it is that the
what this part of the brain is doing is
generating states of of Consciousness
it's the whole the whole reason that the
that the arousal activating systems are
there I have to say because when I first
when I first started reading the the
your work on affect and the way you were
approaching Consciousness I remember
also initially thinking this might this
is a bit out there so when you say like
people people might think it's crazy and
stuff I I can get where you're coming
from but the more you read it the more
you see the evidence the more you talk
about it it it becomes very it almost
becomes very obvious it's almost like
you're highlighting a problem that we've
been ignoring for quite some time how do
you feel about it do you feel like it's
it's it's about time people took this
approach or or do you think it's gaining
some Traction in the way people perceive
the problem um well I'll tell you since
we started our conversation this
conversation now um You you we were
talking about my recent trip to
Boston and um other speakers at that
meeting uh there's Mike Levan Chris
Fields um Carl friston um uh um what's
his name um Richard I forget his
surname Watson yes you know these are
apologies Richard Watson if you're
watching these are um really really
outstanding Minds you know and so I I my
paper I said to them look uh you know I
wanted to because the conference was
mostly about biological versus
artificial uh minds and um I said you
know I'm doing work in that area and I
really want to get there to talk to you
guys about this but I want to spend at
least the first half of my talk just
setting out my stall for why I believe
that the we're looking in the wrong
place it's not cortical it's a it's you
know it's a brain stem function and it's
an affective function and so on and um I
set out all the evidence for them I said
the reason I'm doing this is because to
my great surprise you know many people
still you know don't believe this and I
just I just can't understand it what am
I doing wrong that you know that I'm
can't you see the evidence and so so at
that conference in in because you're
asking me did is it gaining traction all
of those guys who I just mentioned they
all were 100% onite you know so yeah I I
think well gosh you know so that's very
very gratifying but I want to while I'm
busy saying immodest things um I want to
go back a little bit earlier than this
Boston Congress I mean Symposium uh you
know Tom Nagel the other day the
Consciousness conference he he gave the
keynote paper um and he Tom Nagel who
wrote the 1974 paper what is it like to
be about spoke about everything that's
happened since then in Consciousness
studies and mean it's really like the
kind of the the great grandfather of of
of of the modern philosophy of of of of
Consciousness um he's in his talk about
2third of the way through it I mean I
couldn't believe my ears I'm sitting
sitting there listening to Tom Nagel
It's a Wonderful treat you know G giving
us this great sweeping sort of
description of where he started and
where things have gone since then and
where things are now and where how he
sees the future how does he see the
future well he says I think this guy
called Mark somms is doing the right
thing he's he's pointed out that
feelings are intrinsically conscious
States and I think that's right you know
and I think that that's the way forward
I thought wow I've arrived you know
Tom in that he name check two people one
was Mark SS the other one was bar
Spinosa wow that's I mean that's a lot
uh that's that's that's one of the best
name drops you can
get from I mean if you think of Tom Nel
it's he's he's like the father of modern
philosophy of mind at this point the Tom
Nagel's probably the most quoted
philosopher and I think David Chas with
his heart problem is probably follows
right after but so that that's pretty
epic yeah yeah I mean I I was really I
mean not only because remember you asked
me is it gaining traction I mean I
wasn't only gratified and I was deeply
gratified but I was to tell you the
truth I was frankly surprised you know I
really I really I would never have
thought that Tom Nagel would say no
actually I think we are making progress
toward a physical theory of of of
experience you know that's that's that's
really news well well I just want to say
congrats if that comes out of Tom's
mouth it must have been surreal in the
moment yeah it was it really was I mean
but even from my own experience Mark
when I speak to when I spoke to Carl FR
when I spoke to these other guys about
your work it there's clearly a huge
respect for it there's these guys
clearly understand it they know what
you're talking about and they think the
approach is is is a good approach it's
not it's not one that they're
discounting when they when they discuss
these
matters yes that's that's um no I I I
really I I think that it's true to say
that it is gaining traction and but it's
also true to say that it wasn't the case
initially you know it's um because I
also at the time when I I remember when
I first started the podcast they were
some people who who think cuz I think
they tend to associate your Viewpoint at
this point with just an ancient brain um
and there's almost a negative
connotation to saying those words as if
you're you're talking about something
ancient in itself well yeah no and I I
understand where that comes from you
know it's because in fact I I must say I
blame Paul mlan for that you know this
whole thing about the Triune brain that
you know that there's this kind of
carttoon idea that there's a Reptilian
Brain you know sort of trapped inside of
our inside of our brains now so I want
to make clear that when I say ancient
what I mean is phog gentically ancient
in the sense that
because we have because all vertebrates
have the architecture of the upper brain
stem that I'm talking about because we
share with all vertebrates a reticular
activating system and a per aqueductal
gray that means we have a common
ancestor that had that structure the
common ancestor of all vertebrates is
550 million years ago so I'm talking
about that guy the 550 million years ago
that's what's ancient I'm saying that
this structure if evolved and what that
what that means is that the dawn of
Consciousness if I'm right that this
structure is what's generating the the
brw feeling you know the basic the most
elementary form of Consciousness the
dawn of Consciousness was at least 500
at least 550 million years ago that's
what I mean by ancient I think there's
there's there's a lot of
misinterpretations but because of the
fact that you're going to these
conferences you have people like Tom
Nagel now obviously supporting you
hopefully people understand it more or
give it more time in order to gain that
understanding because I think that's a
fundamental approach is to actually read
your work read your papers and then draw
a better
conclusion yes you I suppose the you
know the best thing that can happen is
that people read your work and they're
persuaded by it um the the second the
second best or middle thing out of three
that can happen is they read your work
and they disagree with you and they
reject it the worst thing that can
happen is that they just ignore it
completely so you know even even when
you initially get um negative uh know
push back at least it's not just
completely overlooked yes you know it's
true it's sometimes naming a theory well
gives it that that that that negative
push back you need so like sometimes
saying things like the ancient brain is
like Keith Frankish or denn saying it's
an illusion it it helps with the name
that illusionism gives it that push that
it almost needs time while you're on
that subject I know we we're nearly out
of time but I want to I want to say
something else about feeling um which is
that um unlike perception it cannot be
an illusion uh you you you can't say uh
you you are currently having the
illusion that you're in pain uh you you
you you just are in pain uh you you
can't say that um you having the
illusion that you're sad
you might say you have no good reason to
be sad but still you're sad and I think
that that's also important you know that
when we when we speak about um about um
what do we mean by Consciousness as an
illusion or I I I think it it's not this
doesn't have exactly the same meaning
when you speak about an illusion that
the brain constructs its own sort out of
its own ingredients it constructs uh the
illusion of a three-dimensional world
out there with colors uh that actually
the colors are a product of your brain
rather than a rather than a property of
the world um feeling it's a because it's
about yourself you know it just is what
it is it's it's you can't have illusory
feelings and it's yeah because I was
just about to say it's almost like the
argument of illusionism can't work
against your view of Consciousness
because it's fundamentally talking about
different things because the the
illusion has come at it from a very much
cortical perspective in the first place
so yes now I realize while we're
speaking about this that I didn't
address a point you made earlier and it
suddenly becomes relevant again now you
said what did I mean when I say that
that that perception contextualizes
affect um and this is exactly the right
place to come back to that so how it
works is that you have the feeling
that's just that is just the
consciousness then it's a matter of what
that what what is causing that feeling
and what can I do about that feeling so
I I like to use this um termin this um
this
wording but of course I'm translating
something into words that is not
verbal it is first of all the creature
feels like this it's just raw feeling I
feel like this and then secondly it's a
matter of I feel like this about that
and so the and so the affect is as it
were applied to the context within which
it's with within which it's occurring so
this oh so it's these things that are
making me feel like this and it's there
that I can do something about this
feeling and so this is what I mean when
I say we feel our way into our
cognitions and we feel our way into our
perceptions um yeah like that approach
yeah so so the the you said it's good to
have a catch phrase catchy phrase you
said it it's it's good to have a
controversial one but the I was somebody
recently wrote a a review of different
theories of Consciousness and they
wanted me to tell them what's my theory
called you know so I said I'm calling it
The felt uncertainty it's the felt
uncertainty Theory and um I think that
that's another way in which you can put
what I've just said now it's like I'm
you know it's it's like the common
currency is uncertainty it's like I feel
like this uh in other words I'm I'm I'm
I'm I'm not in a state of certainty
otherwise you wouldn't be feeling the
feeling always remember is a deviation
from homeostasis and then it's a matter
of you know
so you apply that uncertainty to your to
your actions um feeling your way through
is this working is that working is this
working is that working you know so it's
a it's a matter of um affects uh sort of
um you palpate your confidence in your
current Action Program on the basis of
whether or not it is moving the needle
in the right direction effectively so so
it's it's um I like to put it like in
fact it was Carl who put it like this he
said that um if things are turning out
as expected on the basis of my actions
if things are turning out as expected
that's good and if uncertainty prevails
that's
bad okay yeah so it sort of it allows
you to gauge the environment and
interact with it in a very successful
Manner and to maintain
homeostatic uh in order to maintain
homostasis sorry order to maintain
homeostasis the felt will you call it
the felt uncertainty principle yeah
that's it's quite a nice I was thinking
about it as well before coming into this
conversation how call has one of his
papers he calls it I I am therefore I
think Kevin Mitchell has I feel
therefore I am I mean I move therefore I
am and you could make it I feel
therefore I am is another one yeah just
to just to add that to the to the
lecture Series in the future um Mark
before we finish one last thing about
this um the conference was about AI
anything you want to add about feeling
and artificial intelligence and the
implications for the
future yes uh I I am working um with a
team of um physicists and and uh
roboticists and and computer scientists
on an um an AR arcial Consciousness
we've been at it for about two years um
we we've got some good funding from the
opers by the way um and um we we're now
going into our second phase and um you
know I I I I'm really very optimistic
about what we're doing there um we're
trying because we believe that we've
isolated at least in Broad outline the
causal mechanism you know how how
feelings are generated how and why they
generated if you've if you've done that
uh if you really have done that then you
should be able to engineer it in fact it
was Richard feineman who said right at
the end of his life it was found on his
on his Blackboard if I can't create it I
don't understand it and so you know this
is what we're trying to do we're saying
well if this really is the mechanism
then we should be able to engineer
artificial feelings remember we're not
creating a living thing we're creating a
an artificial agent that has exactly the
mechanisms I was describing to you
earlier about different needs and having
to balance those needs and they are
intrinsically veilance to and for that
agent and they are categorically
distinct and etc etc and then this
should be able to display the kinds of
behaviors that I was describing to you
the where you can feel your way through
a problem come up with novel Solutions
it should display voluntary behaviors
and it should be able able to survive in
unpredicted environments and so on so
these are the sorts of things we're
doing and I really do believe it's a
matter not of whether but when uh we'll
we'll succeed with that it's another
story about how do you persuade your
colleagues you know the the problem of
other minds and all of that is not a
small thing uh what what we are going to
be doing is having a symposium with
interest parties where we must determine
in advance what will be acceptable
criteria you know that you can't say
there's no way that you will ever
persuade me at all you know you have to
say well what will persuade you yes and
um and then the ethics of that you know
we we must always always always keep
very clear in our minds that the the
ethical there's two sets of ethical
problems the one is you know the one
that people most frequently refer to is
but you you're going to create these
super intelligent uh creatures that are
trying to survive and they're going to
compete with us and you know that's bad
for us but we must also remember that if
you create a an artificial Consciousness
if it feels uh then you know it can
suffer and uh it you have to be very
careful about what are you what are you
producing here you know and it's all of
the problems that we have in animal
research uh become relevant then to this
sort of research too Mark I'm sorry I
don't know how much time you have left
but I'm so curious to know how does one
even approach this how do you even start
building this sort of artificial
complexity well um you start with the
formalisms that uh was Carl and I
published a paper in 2018 you know he
published that brilliant paper in
2013 called Life as we know it and there
he reduced two formalisms uh the
mechanisms of fundamentally it was the
mechanisms of homeostasis that's what
because the whole mechanism of
self-organization is what underwrites
the mechanism of homeostasis when he
says Life as we know it I mean
homeostasis is the mechanism of Life as
we know it it's it's what distinguishes
living things um so what was I saying
yeah so so that the formalisms that he
developed to explain uh homeostasis we
extended those formalisms to explain
felt homeostasis in our 2018 paper and
uh then you know I I got this team
together and we're using those to
develop Al that formalism to develop
algorithms to create artificial agents
that have homeostatic needs in order for
them to continue to survive it's just a
simple mechanical unpacking of this
thing it's creating the exactly those
Dynamics uh in an artificial agent and
um and creating an environment within
which uh we can have the sorts of um
dynamics that we need in other words
changing so the the agent has to meet
various needs of its own like power
supply and all of that and and uh then
the resources where they are we move
them around once it's learned okay this
is this is how if I do this I can
survive then we change it you know and
then we and then we created situations
where it's not just a matter of
exploiting resources but also there's a
hill that it can go up and have a look
around we want to see does it realize
that if I go up there I see the I see so
that's sort of roughly where we are now
we we we're we're um we've got a a long
way to go but a major part of the next
phase that we're going to do is to have
multiple agents so they in where they
have to interact with each other and
they have to they have to um make
inferences about each other's mental
processes um in in in is uh you know as
part of the same thing oh that's super
exciting I'm sorry about the
interruption but I'm going to have to go
it was really great talking to you again
tev Mark it's been a pleasure always and
uh thank you so much for I know you
don't like to call it a round two it
sounds like a boxing match but hopefully
there's a round and many to go as you
continue on this amazing journey thanks
again mark thank you so much thanks for
your interest and your time always
always pleasure
[Music]
cheers